Welcome back to Manufacturing
Foundations. In this episode, we'll
explore capacities, the operational
backbone that powers the planning
defined by your BOMs and routings.
On Business Central, by clicking into
capacities, [music] you can access work
centers, machine centers, and related
setup pages that drives production
scheduling.
Today, we'll explore work centers,
machine centers, work shifts, and shop
calendar.
Work shifts are the smallest building
blocks.
Contoso has two shifts, code one for the
first shift, and code two for the second
shift. These are reusable labels that
you assign to [music] working days in a
shop calendar.
Shop calendars combine shifts with
working days to define when your shop
floor operates.
Contoso Coffee has two calendars.
If we explore one shift and open working
days, we can see five rows, Monday
through Friday. Each assigned to work
shift one, from 8:00 a.m. to 4:00 p.m.
That's five 8-hour days per week.
For the two shifts calendar, every
weekday has two rows, shift one and
shift two. This doubles available time
per day.
A work center using two shifts can
schedule 16 hours per day instead of
eight.
You can also define holidays on a shop
calendar.
Here you see dates when the shop floor
does not operate. For this shift, we can
see bank holidays and a maintenance week
on last week of June.
Work centers are the core capacity
resources.
If we open the assembly department, the
work center group code is one,
production department.
Work center groups represent the higher
organizational rank for reporting and
cost aggregation.
Contoso Coffee uses group one for the
production department and group five for
subcontractors.
Every work center belongs [music] to
exactly one group and are useful for
costing.
On the posting [music] tab, we can see
operational fields such as direct unit
cost, indirect cost percentage, and
overhead rate. Adding everything to the
unit cost field.
On the scheduling tab, we can define the
unit of measure, capacity, efficiency,
and the shop calendar the work center
follows.
The assembly department uses one shift.
If we check the painting department
instead, they use the shop calendar two
shifts, allowing them to schedule 16
[music] hours per weekday instead of
eight.
Machine centers sit below work centers.
They represent individual machines or
stations and are always part of a work
center.
The machine center flushing manual is
part of the work center number 100,
>> [music]
>> the assembly department.
Machine centers inherit their calendar
from the parent, but each has its own
capacity, efficiency fields, and routing
setups.
If we go back to work centers for a
moment and we activate consolidated
calendar, the work center's capacity
[music]
won't be defined by the work center
card, but compute the sum of its machine
centers.
Everything you've set up comes together
when you calculate the calendar.
If we go back to the work center [music]
list, we can see which work centers use
each shop calendar.
For one shift, we had one maintenance
week beginning of July and affects work
centers [music] 100, 200, and 500.
We can now calculate the work center
[music] calendar and explore the
calendar matrix.
The work center calendar matrix shows
capacity values based on the shop
calendar defined.
Let's look at the weekly values.
Remember we had a maintenance week end
of June?
For week 27, [music] work centers 100,
200, and 500 show no capacity, matching
the maintenance week.
But let's explore a bit more the
calendar matrix.
Our weekly capacity the work center 200
[music] is 2,400 minutes of effective
capacity.
If we open our packing department, we
can see it has capacity of one and a
100% efficiency. Let's say we add
another packing table [music] and we
decrease the efficiency to an 80%.
If we want to apply those changes,
[music]
we need to calculate the work center
calendar to be reflected on the calendar
matrix.
Let's see how that is changed [music]
from the 2,400 effective minutes we had
previously.
Each working day has now a total [music]
capacity of 960 minutes, but effectively
only 768 minutes per day, which adds to
the total of 3,840
minutes weekly.
Time to see the capacity model [music]
in action.
We will create a new production order
for 50 units of our airpot coffee maker.
Let's say we need it for June 19th.
Once we click refresh production order,
the system calculates when production
must start and finish. Production will
take around four business days to finish
from 15th to the 18th.
But, what happens if we schedule it for
July 7th instead?
This time production takes from June
24th to July 6th, taking 13 natural days
instead of the previously four business
days.
If we inspect airpot's routing, all
operations go through [music] our work
centers 100 and 200, which will be
closed for the maintenance weekend of
June.
Business Central uses calendar [music]
entries for scheduling your production
against your capacities.
>> [music]
>> You've now seen how Business Central's
capacity model works from the bottom up.
Work shifts [music] and shop calendars
assemble production times, work centers
and machine centers carry capacity
[music] and efficiency settings, and
calendar entries turn all of this into
available production time.
Thanks for watching [music] and see you
next time.